Finding Aid for Ruggles & Rademaker records, 1868-1931
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Ruggles & Rademaker records
1868-1931
Ruggles & Rademaker.
85639 Bb.2/2
Records of the Ruggles & Rademaker of Manistee, Michigan, and of the predecessor land and lumber enterprises of Charles Ruggles and Edward Buckley, including the Buckley and Douglas Lumber Co., the Manistee and Northeastern Railroad, and the Emeline Bath Co. of Chicago, Ill. Financial records and business correspondence of Edward Buckley, Charles Ruggles, and John Rademaker; also files concerning lawsuit between Ruggles and Buckley.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
48 linear feet
1 oversize volumes
18 microfilms
The record group was the gift of the Charles F. Ruggles estate (donor no. 3132 ) and came to the library in 1955.
Periodic additions to the records expected.
The record group is open to research.
Charles F. Ruggles was born at Naples, Maine on March 3, 1846. He moved to Wisconsin some time in the 1850s, eventually going into the timber estimating business with his father. Around 1866, he established himself as a lumberman with his headquarters in Manistee, Michigan. Over the years, he acquired timber land in Michigan, Minnesota, California, and the Carolinas.
In 1880, Ruggles as a silent partner was instrumental in guiding the negotiations which led to the partnership between Edward Buckley and William Douglas for purposes of establishing a logging and lumber manufacturing business. In 1886, this firm acquired the Ruddock & Nuttall mill property. The Buckley and Douglas Lumber Company was formally incorporated in 1892.
The following years were marked by litigation between Ruggles and Buckley. In 1906 was awarded one million dollars from Buckley. In 1926, Buckley was awarded one hundred thousand dollars from Ruggles.
In 1920, Ruggles purchased the Buckley & Douglas lumber company in Manistee, and then in partnership with John Henry Rademaker, built and developed what was recognized as the largest salt plant in the world. The two partners would have a falling out, leading to the case of Rademaker v. Ruggles. The plant was sold in 1931 to the Morton Salt Company.
Ruggles died August 21, 1930.
This record group, although named for the salt company owned and operated by Charles F. Ruggles and John Henry Rademaker from 1920 to its sale in 1931, is also an accumulation of records of the business enterprises and land dealings of Charles Ruggles beginning in 1866 and of the partnership operations of Ruggles and Edward Buckley. Included are business correspondence, financial records, organizational materials, and litigation files. Many of the financial records have been microfilmed.
Subjects:
Baths.; Buckley, Edward, b. 1842.; Buckley & Douglas Lumber Company.; Business records.; Chicago (Ill.)--Businesses.; Emeline Bath Company (Chicago, Ill.); Logging--Michigan--Manistee.; Lumbering--Michigan--Manistee.; Manistee and Northeastern Railroad.; Manistee (Mich.)--Economic conditions.; Rademaker, John.; Railroads--Michigan.; Ruggles, Charles, 1846-1930.; Salt industry and trade--Michigan--Manistee.; Ruggles & Rademaker.
- Corporate records of Ruggles and Buckley business enterprises
  - Buckley and Douglas Lumber Company
    - Balance sheets, 1892-1921 (Box 6)
    - Board of Directors minutes, 1892-1922 (Box 6)
  - Manistee and Northeastern Railroad
    - Board of Directors minutes, 1887-1919 (Box 6)
    - Miscellaneous papers, 1887-1919 (Box 6)
  - Trial Balances of Edward Buckley's books, 1881-1903 (Box 7)
  - Trial Balance (unidentified), 1875 (Box 7)
  - Balance sheets of Charles Ruggles, 1869-1879 (Box 7)
  - Trial Balance of Charles Ruggles, 1882 (Box 7)
  - Edward Buckley inventories, 1899-1903 (Box 7)
  - Consolidated Speculation Record, 1878-1879 (Box 7)
  - Papers concerning the Chicago and Manistee bath houses (Box 7)
  - Camp operations records, 1896-1907 (Box 7)
  - Estimators Field Notes, Lower Peninsula, 1868-1877 (Box 10)
    (see outsize material for index)
  - Estimators Field Notes, Upper Peninsula, 1882-1910 (Box 10)
  - Woods plat and index, 1868-1877 (Volume 1)
    (indexes Estimators Field Notes, Lower Peninsula)
  - California mill surveys (Box 11)
  - Time statements of employees, 1915-1918 (Box 12)
  - Time statements of employees, 1922; 1928-1931 (Box 13)
  - Papers concerning the Hopper Manufacturing Company deal (Box 14)
  - Papers concerning the Rainy Lake Company. (Box 14)
  - Miscellaneous Papers (Box 14)
  - Contracts and deeds, 1870-1931 (Box 43)
  - Daybooks of Emeline Bath company, 1886-1891 (Box 48)
  - Ledger of Emeline Bath Company, 1886-1891 (Box 48)
  - Minute book of the Rainy Lake Company, 1903-1906 (Box 48)
  - Amador County, California financial records, 1918-1923 (Box 48)
  - Record of credit reports on merchants in Manistee and elsewhere (Box 48)
- Letterpress books, 1868-1930
  - Outgoing letters, 1868-1880 (Box 15)
  - Outgoing letters, 1880-1889 (Box 16)
  - Private, 1869-1883 (Box 16)
  - Private, 1873-1891 (Box 17)
  - Private, 1885-1890 (Box 18)
  - Personal (incoming), 1899-1901 (Box 18)
  - Personal (incoming), 1901-1907 (Box 19)
  - General Business (incoming)
    - 1898-1905 (Box 20)
    - 1905-1908 (Box 21)
    - 1908-1910 (Box 22)
    - 1911-1914 (Box 23)
    - 1914-1918 (Box 24)
    - 1922-1928 (Box 25)
  - General Business (outgoing), 1903-1930 (Box 26)
  - Minnesota
    - Edward Buckley (incoming), 1882-1901 (Box 27)
    - General (incoming), 1896-1905 (Box 28)
    - General (incoming), 1905-1912 (Box 29)
    - General (incoming), 1912-1916 (Box 30)
    - General (incoming), 1916-1922 (Box 31)
    - General (incoming), 1922-1924 (Box 32)
    - General (outgoing), 1903-1927 (Box 32)
    - General (outgoing), 1927-1930 (Box 33)
  - Rainy Lake Company Letterpress book, 1903-1906 (Box 33)
  - California
    - General (incoming), 1908-1911 (Box 33)
    - General (incoming), 1912-1918 (Box 34)
    - General (incoming), 1918-1920 (Box 35)
    - General (incoming), 1920-1924 (Box 36)
    - General (incoming), 1924-1925 (Box 37)
    - General (outgoing), 1909-1930 (Box 37)
  - Michigan
    - General (incoming), 1897-1910 (Box 38)
    - General (incoming), 1910-1916 (Box 39)
    - General (incoming), 1916-1924 (Box 40)
    - General (incoming), 1924-1927 (Box 41)
  - Correspondence from John Rademaker to Charles Ruggles, 1910-1924 (Box 41)
  - South Carolina Lumber Company, 1909-1917 (Box 41)
  - Personal (outgoing), 1903-1930 (Box 42)
  - Miscellaneous papers (Box 42)
- Litigation, 1880-1926
  - Ruggles vs. Buckley lawsuit, 1880-1926
    - 1880-1902 (Box 1)
    - 1903-1906 (Box 2)
    - 1906-1908 (Box 3)
    - 1909-1912 (Box 4)
    - 1913-1926 (Box 5)
    - undated (Box 5)
  - Hulett vs. Ruggles lawsuit, circa 1884-1886 (Box 8)
  - Hulett vs. Ruggles lawsuit, circa 1884-1886 (Box 9)
- Ruggles & Rademaker corporate records
  - Employee time sheets, 1921-1929
    - 1921-1925 (Box 44)
    - 1926-1929 (Box 44)
  - Trial Balances, 1920-1928 (Box 45)
  - Employee accident reports, 1921-1928 (Box 46)
  - Income tax papers, 1921-1930 (Box 47)
  - Letterpress books (outgoing), 1920-1930 (Box 47)
- Financial Records, microfilm
  - Daybooks
    - 1881-1883 (Box 49, Reel 1)
    - 1883-1884 (Box 49, Reel 1)
    - 1884-1886 (Box 49, Reel 2)
    - 1886-1887 (Box 49, Reel 2)
    - 1887-1888 (Box 49, Reel 3)
    - 1888 (Box 49, Reel 3)
    - 1888-1889 (Box 49, Reel 4)
    - 1889-1890 (Box 49, Reel 4)
    - 1890 (Box 49, Reel 5)
    - 1890-1891 (Box 49, Reel 5)
    - 1891-1892 (Box 49, Reel 6)
    - 1892 (Box 49, Reel 6)
    - 1892-1893 (Box 49, Reel 7)
    - 1893-1894 (Box 49, Reel 7)
    - 1894-1896 (Box 49, Reel 8)
    - 1897-1906 (Box 49, Reel 8)
    - 1907-1910 (Box 49, Reel 8)
  - Operating expenses, 1904-1907 (Box 49, Reel 9)
  - Ledgers
    - 1881-1887 (Box 49, Reel 9)
    - 1880-1892 (Box 49, Reel 9)
    - 1893-1910 (Box 49, Reel 10)
  - Land Ledger, 1882-1902 (Box 49, Reel 10)
  - Time book, 1894-1899 (Box 49, Reel 10)
  - Ruggles & Rademaker Cashbook
    - 1924-1926 (Box 49, Reel 11)
    - (pp 1-217), 1926-1928 (Box 49, Reel 11)
    - (pp 218-end), 1926-1928 (Box 49, Reel 12)
    - 1928 (Box 49, Reel 12)
    - 1929-1930 (Box 49, Reel 12)
  - Ruggles & Rademaker Cost ledger
    - 1920-1927 (Box 49, Reel 13)
    - 1928 (Box 49, Reel 13)
  - Ruggles & Rademaker Journal
    - 1920-1924 (Box 49, Reel 14)
    - 1924-1928 (Box 49, Reel 15)
    - 1928-1930 (Box 49, Reel 15)
  - Ruggles & Rademaker Ledger, 1920-1928 (Box 49, Reel 16)
  - Weekly Financial Reports, 1902-1911 (Box 49, Reel 16)
  - Emeline Bath Co., 1887-1891 (Box 49, Reel 16)
  - Manistee and Northeastern Railway (Box 49, Reel 17)
  - Vouchers
    - 1894-1897 (Box 49, Reel 17)
    - 1898-1900 (Box 49, Reel 17)
    - 1900-1903 (Box 49, Reel 17)
  - Bills for Collection (Box 49, Reel 17)
  - Lumber Department Records (Box 49, Reel 17)
  - Manistee and Northeastern Railway Record of Claims, 1904-1906 (Box 49, Reel 18)
  - Records of Steam Barge Edward Buckley, Record Books 1-4 (Box 49, Reel 18)
Related Material
The library also has a small collection of personal Charles Ruggles papers. These papers relate mainly to his work as co-founder of the American Judicature Society, an organization concerned with improving the efficiency of the American judicial system.